Guide to the Workers Party Records TAM.136
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Workers Party and Independent Socialist League Records
1945-1958
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Independent Socialist League
Workers Party (1940-1949)
TAM.136
3 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
The Workers Party, a Trotskyist organization founded and led by Max Shachtman, split from the Socialist Workers Party in 1940, holding the Soviet Union to be a novel exploitative social formation, bureaucratic collectivism. Opposing the "two camps" of imperialism, the WP led struggles against the World War II no-strike pledge, and published Labor Action, and The New International, both continuing until 1958, when the successor to the WP, the Independent Socialist League (1949-1958) merged with the Socialist Party. The collection contains minutes, correspondence, reports and resolutions, study guides, memorandums and position papers, and newsletters. Much of the material reflects the lively internal debates and factional conflicts within both the Workers Party and the Independent Socialist League.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated in 1988; additional materials were donated in 2005. The accession number associated with this gift is 1988.004.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The material is organized into one series.
Missing Title
Series I: General Files
Historical Note
The Workers Party (1940-1949), a Trotskyist organization founded and led by Max Shachtman, split from the Socialist Workers Party in 1940, holding the Soviet Union to be a novel exploitative social formation, bureaucratic collectivism. Opposing the "two camps" of imperialism, the WP led struggles against the World War II no-strike pledge, and published Labor Action, a rank-and-file newspaper, and The New International, a political/theoretical journal, both continuing until 1958, when the successor to the WP, the Independent Socialist League (1949-1958) merged with the Socialist Party. The Workers Party was a source for many of the ideas, personalities and journals of the post-World War II non- and anti-communist left, and former members influenced the development of the Socialist Party and helped found the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (later Democratic Socialists of America).
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Max Shachtman Papers (Tamiment 103).
Oral History of the American Left (Oral Histories 2)
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains national committee and convention minutes for both the Workers Party and Independent Socialist League, correspondence, including subscription and editorial correspondence for Labor Action and The New International, reports, including several from local branches, study guides and other materials produced by the Education Department, resolutions, memorandums and position papers, and newsletters, including Labor Vets Bulletin, produced by Party members active in the American Veterans Committee. Much of the material reflects the lively internal debates and factional conflicts within both the Workers Party and the Independent Socialist League. Notable individuals represented, in addition to Max Shachtman, include Ernest Rice McKinney (WP National Secretary), Nathan Gould (Director of Organization), and Gordon Haskell ( Labor Action). Also of note is the folder re the "Third Camp Contact Committee," an attempt to establish links between Western and developing countries' socialists, pacifists, and nationalists.
Newsletters.; Minutes (administrative records); Reports.; Communism -- United States -- 20th century; Labor movement -- United States -- 20th century.; Socialism -- United States -- 20th century.; Veterans |z United States |x Political activity |y 1945-1960.; World War, 1939-1945 |x Veterans |z United States |v Periodicals.; Correspondence.; Labor action (New York, N.Y.); American Veterans Committee; Labor vets bulletin; New international; Shachtman, Max, 1903-1972; Workers Party (1940-1949); Independent Socialist League; Socialist Workers Party; McKinney, Ernest Rice, 1886-1984; Haskell, Gordon; Gould, Nathan
- Series I: General Files
  - Active Workers Conference, Aug 1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - City Convention, New York, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Constitutions, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Convention, Fourth National (May 27-31, 1946) Minutes (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Convention, Fifth National (Nov 1947) Minutes (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Convention, Fifth National (Nov 1947) Materials: Active Workers Conference Minutes (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Convention, Fifth National (Nov 1947) Materials: Directives - Prices Campaign (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Convention, Fifth National (Nov 1947) Materials: Directives - Labor Action (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Convention, Fifth National (Nov 1947) Materials: Finances (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Convention, Fifth National (Nov 1947) Materials: National Committee Plenum Minutes, May 1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Convention, Fifth National (Nov 1947) Materials: Organization Directives, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Convention, Fifth National (Nov 1947) Materials: Perspectives - Labor Action, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Convention, Fifth National (Nov 1947) Materials: State of the Party Reporsts, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Convention (March 1949) Materials, 1945-1949 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Education Department: Labor Movement, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Education Department: Marxism, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Education Department: Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Education Department: The Party, Fourth International, Russia, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Independent Socialist League Minutes, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Independent Socialist League Minutes, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Independent Socialist League Minutes, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Independent Socialist League Minutes, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Independent Socialist League Minutes, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Labor Action Correspondence, Domestic, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Labor Action Correspondence, Domestic, 1954-1957 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Labor Action Correspondence, Foreign, 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Labor Action Correspondence, Foreign, 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Labor Action Correspondence, Foreign, 1954-1956 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Labor Action: Writers Guides, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Labor Action/New International Correspondence, Foreign: Mailing Returns, 1951-1953 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Labor Vets Bulletin (Labor Veterans Group in AVC), 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Local Branch Reports, 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - McKinney, Ernest Rice (National Secretary) Circulars, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Members Critiques of Party Positions, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Memorial Day Flood, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - National Committee Communications to NC Members/Alternates, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - National Committee Minutes, Sep 25, 1945-Dec 30, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - National Committee Minutes, Jul-46-Dec-46 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - National Committee Plenum (Nov 23-24, 1946) Materials (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - National Office Communications to Local Branches, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Organizational Directives, 1946-1948 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Party Bulletin, Oct 18, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Statements, Theses, etc., undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Third Camp Contact Committee, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Weekly Letters ("To All Branches'), 1946 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Workers Party Records, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Workers Party Records, Miscellaneous, 1940-1944 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Workers Party Records, Miscellaneous, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Workers Party Records, Miscellaneous, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Workers Party Records, Miscellaneous, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Workers Party Records, Miscellaneous, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Workers Party Records, Miscellaneous, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 12)